<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY chapterQFT SYSTEM "chapterQFT.xml">
  <!ENTITY chapterQED SYSTEM "chapterQED.xml">
  <!ENTITY chapterQMperturb SYSTEM "chapterQMperturb.xml">
  <!ENTITY chapterAppendix SYSTEM "chapterAppendix.xml">
  <!ENTITY ssharp "&#223;">
  <!ENTITY ouml "&#246;">
  <!ENTITY uuml "&#252;">
]>

<article>
    <articleinfo>
        <title>Quantum Field Theory and Quantum Mechanics</title>
        <mathinclude>
            \usepackage{braket}
            \input macros.tex
        </mathinclude>
    </articleinfo>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <p>
            The aim of these (work in progress) notes is to use the Standard
            Model of particle physics to derive all equations in quantum
            mechanics (and quantum field theory) that we need for our research.
        </p>
        <p>
            We start by deriving the electroweak Standard Model from the
            <m>SU(2)\times U(1)</m> symmetry and couple other (standard)
            assumptions in the quantum field theory. After that, we only want
            to derive things and make nonrelativistic limits or other
            approximations in order to derive everything else in quantum
            mechanics. In particular we show how to derive the
            Dirac and Schr&ouml;dinger equations (as a low energy limit). We
            then show some particular ways to solve those equations, like
            perturbation theory, scattering theory, ...
        </p>
        <p>
            The goal is to have a complete theory on about 30 or 40 pages and
            then lots of examples (arbitrarily long), that use the theory (but
            do not develop new ideas), so that one can learn how the theory
            works from the examples.
            For instance, one can ask "why is there the term <m>({\bf p}-e{\bf A})^2</m> in the Schr&ouml;dinger equation for electromagnetic
            field, why this and not something else?" or "why
            is there the <m>\boldsymbol\sigma\cdot{\bf B}</m> term in the Pauli
            equation?", to find the answer, one just finds the Pauli equation
            in the theory and then looks at the derivation, so in this case one
            quickly finds that it follows from the minimal coupling in QED,
            e.g. it's the easiest way how electron-foton interaction can be
            coupled, e.g. the <m>U(1)</m> symmetry. Nice thing about QFT is
            that one can find really nice geometrical reasons why things
            are that way and not some other way (just open any advance book on
            QFT), but the problem is that basically nowhere is some easy (but
            correct) translation of those results to regular QM, so that
            everything fits into just couple dozens pages, so that it can serve
            as a reference.
        </p>
        <p>
            The advantage of this top-down approach is that it is easy to see
            where things come from and also to understand exactly what
            approximations one is using when dealing with any equation in QM.
            However, as is well-known in physics, to be a good physicist one
            has to understand all the approaches, e.g. both top-down and
            bottom-up and all other approaches to QM and QFT, because there are
            no two approaches that would be 100% equivalent, so one has to use
            the right approach for the particular problem. So these notes do
            not aspire to be the right way to teach QM, but rather to serve as
            a reference to get quickly oriented and to find the equations to
            start from.
        </p>
    </section>
    &chapterQFT;
    <section>
        <title>Quantum Mechanics</title>
        &chapterQED;
        &chapterQMperturb;
    </section>
    &chapterAppendix;
</article>
